<?xml-model href="../schema/intro_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<introduction>

<Title>SHAKESPEARE'S TRAGEDY OF ROMEO AND JULIET</Title>


<preface>
<p number= "1">This edition of _Romeo and Juliet_, first published in 1879, is now
thoroughly revised on the same general plan as its predecessors in the
new series.</p>

<p number= "2">While I have omitted most of the notes on textual variations, I have
retained a sufficient number to illustrate the curious and significant
differences between the first and second quartos. Among the many new
notes are some calling attention to portions of the early draft of the
play--some of them very bad--which Shakespeare left unchanged when he
revised it.</p>

<p number= "3">The references to Dowden in the notes are to his recent and valuable
edition of the play, which I did not see until this of mine was on the
point of going to the printer. The quotation on page 288 of the Appendix
is from his _Shakspere: His Mind and Art_, which, by the way, was
reprinted in this country at my suggestion.</p>
</preface>


<contents>
  <section title ="INTRODUCTION TO ROMEO AND JULIET">                          
     <subsection n="1">INTRODUCTION TO ROMEO AND JULIET</subsection>                                   
     <subsection n="2">The Sources of the Plot</subsection>                                   
     <subsection n="3">General Comments on the Play</subsection>                              
   </section>

  <section title="ROMEO AND JULIET">                                   
      <act Number ="1">Act I</act>                                                     
      <act Number ="2">Act II</act>                                                    
      <act Number ="3">Act III</act>                                                   
      <act Number ="4">Act IV</act>
      <act Number ="5">Act V</act>                                                  
</section>
<section title="Notes"/>

<section title ="Appendix">
  <subsection n="1">Concerning Arthur Brooke</subsection>                                 
  <subsection n="2">Comments on Some of the Characters</subsection>                       
  <subsection n="3">The Time-Analysis of the Play</subsection>                            
  <subsection n="4">List of Characters in the Play</subsection>                          
</section>

<section title="INDEX OF WORDS AND PHRASES EXPLAINED"/>

<Illustration description= "FUNERAL OF JULIET"/>
<Illustration description= "Verona"/>
</contents>

<history_of_play>
  <edition no="1" year="1597">The earliest edition of _Romeo and Juliet_, so far as we know, was a quarto printed in 1597, the title-page of which asserts that "it hath been often (with great applause) plaid publiquely."</edition>
  <edition no="2" year="1599">A second quarto appeared in 1599, declared to be "newly corrected, augmented, and amended."</edition>
  <edition no="additional" year ="1623,1609,1637">Two other quartos appeared before the folio of 1623, one in 1609 and the other undated; and it is doubtful which was the earlier. The undated quarto is the first that bears the name of the author ("Written by W._Shake-speare_"), but this does not occur in some copies of the edition.A fifth quarto was published in 1637.</edition>
  
  <comparison>
    <Description id="1">The first quarto is much shorter than the second, the former having only 2232 lines, including the prologue, while the latter has 3007 lines(Daniel).Some editors believe that the first quarto gives the author's
      first draft of the play, and the second the form it took after he had
      revised and enlarged it; but the majority of the best critics agree
      substantially in the opinion that the first quarto was a pirated
      edition, and represents in an abbreviated and imperfect form the play
      subsequently printed in full in the second. The former was "made up
      partly from copies of portions of the original play, partly from
      recollection and from notes taken during the performance;" the latter
      was from an authentic copy, and a careful comparison of the text with
      the earlier one shows that in the meantime the play "underwent revision,
      received some slight augmentation, and in some few places must have been
      entirely rewritten."</Description>
    
    <passage version="first_quarto"> A marked instance of this rewriting--the only one
      of considerable length--is in ii. 6. 6-37, where the first quarto reads
      thus (spelling and pointing being modernized):--
      <line><speaker char="Jul">Juliet</speaker>Romeo.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Rom">Romeo</speaker>My Juliet, welcome. As do waking eyes Closed in Night's mists attend the frolick Day, So Romeo hath expected Juliet,And thou art come.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Jul">Juliet</speaker>I am, if I be Day,Come to my Sun: shine forth and make me fair.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Rom">Romeo</speaker> All beauteous fairness dwelleth in thine eyes</line>
      <line><speaker char="Jul">Juliet</speaker>Romeo, from thine all brightness doth arise.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Fri">Friar Laurence</speaker>Come, wantons, come, the stealing hours do pass,
        Defer embracements till some fitter time.
        Part for a while, you shall not be alone
        Till holy Church have joined ye both in one.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Rom">Romeo</speaker>Lead, holy Father, all delay seems long</line>
      <line><speaker char="Jul">Juliet</speaker>Make haste, make haste, this lingering doth us wrong.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Jul">Juliet</speaker>Good even to my ghostly confessor.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Fri">Friar Laurence</speaker>Romeo shall thank thee, daughter, for us both.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Jul">Juliet</speaker>As much to him, else is his thanks too much.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Rom">Romeo</speaker>Ah, Juliet, if the measure of thy joy
        Be heap'd like mine and that thy skill be more
        To blazon it, then sweeten with thy breath
        This neighbour air, and let rich music's tongue
        Unfold the imagin'd happiness that both
        Receive in either by this dear encounter.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Jul">Juliet</speaker> Conceit, more rich in matter than in words,
        Brags of his substance, not of ornament.
        They are but beggars that can count their worth;
        But my true love is grown to such excess
        I cannot sum up half my sum of wealth.</line>
      <line><speaker char="Fri">Friar Laurence</speaker>Come, come with me, and we will make short work;
        For, by your leaves, you shall not stay alone
        Till holy church incorporate two in one.</line>
    </passage>
    <Description id="2">The "omission, mutilation, or botching" by which some German editors
      would explain all differences between the earlier and later texts will
      not suffice to account for such divergence as this. "The two dialogues
      do not differ merely in expressiveness and effect; they embody different
      conceptions of the characters;" and yet we cannot doubt that both were
      written by Shakespeare.
      But while the second quarto is "unquestionably our best authority" for
      the text of the play, it is certain that it "was not printed from the
      author's manuscript, but from a transcript, the writer of which was not
      only careless, but thought fit to take unwarrantable liberties with the
      text." The first quarto, with all its faults and imperfections, is often
      useful in the detection and correction of these errors and corruptions,
      and all the modern editors have made more or less use of its readings.
    </Description>
    <Description id="3">The third quarto (1609) was a reprint of the second, from which it
      "differs by a few corrections, and more frequently by additional
      errors." It is from this edition that the text of the first folio is
      taken, with some changes, accidental or intentional, "all generally for
      the worse," except in the punctuation, which is more correct, and the
      stage directions, which are more complete, than in the quarto.</Description>
    <Description id="4">The date of the first draft of the play has been much discussed, but
      cannot be said to have been settled. The majority of the editors believe
      that it was begun as early as 1561, but I think that most of them lay
      too much stress on the Nurse's reference (i. 3. 22, 35) to the
      "earthquake," which occurred "eleven years" earlier, and which these
      critics suppose to have been the one felt in England in 1580.
      Aside from this and other attempts to fix the date by external evidence
      of a doubtful character, the internal evidence confirms the opinion that
      the tragedy was an early work of the poet, and that it was subsequently
      "corrected, augmented, and amended." There is a good deal of rhyme, and
      much of it in the form of alternate rhyme. The alliteration, the
      frequent playing upon words, and the lyrical character of many passages
      also lead to the same conclusion.</Description>
    <Description id="5">The latest editors agree substantially with this view. Herford says:
      "The evidence points to 1594-1595 as the time at which the play was
      substantially composed, though it is tolerably certain that some parts
      of our present text were written as late as 1596-1598, and possibly that
      others are as early as 1591." Dowden sums up the matter thus: "On the
      whole, we might place _Romeo and Juliet_, on grounds of internal
      evidence, near _The Rape of Lucrece_; portions may be earlier in date;
      certain passages of the revised version are certainly later; but I think
      that 1595 may serve as an approximation to a central date, and cannot be
      far astray."
      For myself, while agreeing substantially with these authorities, I think
      that a careful comparison of what are evidently the earliest portions
      of the text with similar work in _Love's Labour's Lost_ (a play revised
      like this, but retaining traces of the original form), _The Two
      Gentlemen of Verona_, and other plays which the critics generally assign
      to 1591 or 1592, proves conclusively that parts of _Romeo and Juliet_
      must be of quite as early a date.</Description>
    <additional_notes>The earliest reference to the play in the literature of the time is in a
      sonnet to Shakespeare by John Weever, written probably in 1595 or 1596,
      though not published until 1599. After referring to _Venus and Adonis_
      and _Lucrece_, Weever adds:--
      
      "_Romeo_, _Richard_, more whose names I know not,
      Their sugred tongues and power attractive beuty
      Say they are saints," etc.
      
 No other allusion of earlier date than the publication of the first quarto has been discovered.</additional_notes>
  </comparison>
</history_of_play>

  <sources_of_plot>
    <Introduction>Girolamo della Corte, in his Storia di Verona, 1594, relates the story
      of the play as a true event occurring in 1303; but the earlier annalists of the city are silent on the subject.
    </Introduction>
    
    <Source ref="s1">
      <author>Masuccio di Salerno</author>
      <name>Collection of Novels</name>
      <date>1476</date>
      <explanation>A tale very similar, the scene of which is laid in Siena, appears in this collection.</explanation>
    </Source>
    
    <Source ref="s2">
      <author>Luigi da Porto</author>
      <name>La Giulietta</name>
      <date>1530</date>
      <explanation>The first source to name the lovers Romeo and Juliet, making them children of rival Veronese houses.</explanation>
    </Source>
    
    <Source ref="s3">
      <author>Adrian Sevin</author>
      <language>French</language>
      <date>1542</date>
      <explanation>The story was retold in French by Adrian Sevin.</explanation>
    </Source>
    
    <Source ref="s4">
      <name>Poetical Version</name>
      <date>1553</date>
      <explanation>A poetical version of the story was published in Venice.</explanation>
    </Source>
    
    <Source ref="s5">
      <author>Bandello</author>
      <name>Novelle</name>
      <date>1554</date>
      <explanation>A version of the story found in Bandello's collection.</explanation>
    </Source>
    
    <Source ref="s6">
      <author>Pierre Boisteau</author>
      <name>Histoire de Deux Amans</name>
      <date>1559</date>
      <language>French</language>
      <explanation>Translated with some variations from Bandello's story.</explanation>
    </Source>
    
    <Source id="s7">
      <author>Arthur Brooke</author>
      <name>Romeus and Juliet</name>
      <date>1562</date>
      <explanation>The earliest English version of the romance, a poem based on Boisteau's novel.</explanation>
    </Source>
    
    <Source id="s8">
      <author>Paynter</author>
      <name>Palace of Pleasure</name>
      <date>1567</date>
      <explanation>A prose translation of Boisteau's novel.</explanation>
    </Source>
    
    <Quote>
      <dialogue>"The tragedy follows the poem with a faithfulness which might be called slavish, were it not that any variation from the course of the old story was entirely unnecessary for the sake of dramatic interest..."</dialogue>
      <commentary>Grant White remarks on Shakespeare's adaptation.</commentary>
    </Quote>
    
    <Quote>
      <dialogue>"Romeo and Juliet owes to Shakespeare only its dramatic form and its poetic decoration."</dialogue>
      <commentary>This highlights Shakespeare's unique contribution to the story's emotional depth.</commentary>
    </Quote>
    
    <Footnote>[1] A translation of La Giulietta, with an historical and
        critical introduction by me, was published in Boston, 1893.
    </Footnote>
  </sources_of_plot>
  

GENERAL COMMENTS ON THE PLAY

Coleridge, in his _Notes and Lectures upon Shakespeare_, says: "The
stage in Shakespeare's time was a naked room with a blanket for a
curtain, but he made it a field for monarchs. That law of unity which
has its foundations, not in the factitious necessity of custom, but in
nature itself, the unity of feeling, is everywhere and at all times
observed by Shakespeare in his plays. Read _Romeo and Juliet_: all is
youth and spring--youth with its follies, its virtues, its
precipitancies; spring with its odours, its flowers, and its transiency.
It is one and the same feeling that commences, goes through, and ends
the play. The old men, the Capulets and the Montagues, are not common
old men; they have an eagerness, a heartiness, a vehemence, the effect
of spring; with Romeo, his change of passion, his sudden marriage, and
his rash death, are all the effects of youth; whilst in Juliet love has
all that is tender and melancholy in the nightingale, all that is
voluptuous in the rose, with whatever is sweet in the freshness of
spring; but it ends with a long deep sigh like the last breeze of the
Italian evening."

The play, like _The Merchant of Venice_, is thoroughly Italian in
atmosphere and colour. The season, though Coleridge refers to it
figuratively as spring, is really midsummer. The time is definitely
fixed by the Nurse's talk about the age of Juliet. She asks Lady Capulet
how long it is to Lammas-tide--that is, to August 1--and the reply is,
"A fortnight and odd days"--sixteen or seventeen days we may suppose,
making the time of the conversation not far from the middle of July.
This is confirmed by allusions to the weather and other natural
phenomena in the play. At the beginning of act iii, for instance,
Benvolio says to his friends:--

"I pray thee, good Mercutio, let's retire;
The day is hot, the Capulets abroad,
And if we meet we shall not scape a brawl,
For now, these hot days, is the mad blood stirring."

When the Nurse goes on the errand to Romeo (ii. 4), Peter carries her
fan, and she finds occasion to use it. "The nights are only softer days,
not made for sleep, but for lingering in moonlit gardens, where the
fruit-tree tops are tipped with silver and the nightingale sings on the
pomegranate bough." It is only in the coolness of the dawn that Friar
Laurence goes forth to gather herbs; and it is

"An hour before the worshipp'd sun
Peer'd forth the golden window of the east,"

that we find Romeo wandering in the grove of sycamore, "with tears
augmenting the fresh morning's dew," because Rosaline will not return
his love.

In one instance, overlooked by the commentators generally, Shakespeare
seems to forget the time of year. In the masquerade scene (i. 5) Old
Capulet bids the servants "quench the fire" because "the room is grown
too hot." In Brooke's poem, where the action covers four or five months,
this scene is in the winter. Shakespeare, in condensing the time to less
than a single week in summer, neglected to omit this reference to a
colder season.

Aside from this little slip, the time is the Italian summer from first
to last. And, as a French critic remarks, "the very form of the language
comes from the South." The tale originated in Italy; "it breathes the
very spirit of her national records, her old family feuds, the amorous
and bloody intrigues which fill her annals. No one can fail to recognize
Italy in its lyric rhythm, its blindness of passion, its blossoming and
abundant vitality, in its brilliant imagery, its bold composition." All
the characters are distinctively Italian. "In total effect," as another
has said, "the play is so Italian that one may read it with increasing
surprise and delight in Verona itself."

Although, as I have said, it is doubtful whether the story has any
historical basis, the Montagues and the Capulets were famous old
families in Verona. Dante alludes to them in the _Purgatorio_ (vi. 107),
though not as enemies:--

"Vieni a veder Montecchi e Cappelletti,
Monaldi e Filippeschi, uom senza cura,
Color gi  tristi, e costor con sospetti."[2]

The palace of the Capulets is to this day pointed out in Verona. It is
degraded to plebeian occupancy, and the only mark of its ancient dignity
is the badge of the family, the _cap_ carved in stone on the inner side
of the entrance to the court, which is of ample size, surrounded by
buildings that probably formed the main part of the mansion, but are now
divided into many tenements. The garden has disappeared, having been
covered with other buildings centuries ago.

The so-called "tomb of Juliet" is in a less disagreeable locality, but
is unquestionably a fraud, though it has been exhibited for a century or
two, and has received many tributes from credulous and sentimental
tourists. It is in the garden of an ancient convent, and consists of an
open, dilapidated stone sarcophagus (perhaps only an old horse-trough),
without inscription or any authentic history. It is kept in a kind of
shed, the walls of which are hung with faded wreaths and other mementoes
from visitors. One pays twenty-five centesimi (five cents) for the
privilege of inspecting it. Byron went to see it in 1816, and writes
(November 6) to his sister Augusta: "I brought away four small pieces
of it for you and the babes (at least the female part of them), and for
Ada and her mother, if she will accept it from you. I thought the
situation more appropriate to the history than if it had been less
blighted. This struck me more than all the antiquities, more even than
the amphitheatre." Maria Louisa, the French empress, got a piece of it,
which she had made into hearts and other forms for bracelets and
necklaces; and many other sentimental ladies followed the royal example
before the mutilation of the relic was prohibited by its guardians.

To return to the play--one would suppose that the keynote was struck
with sufficient clearness in the prologue to indicate Shakespeare's
purpose and the moral lesson that he meant to impress; but many of the
critics have nevertheless failed to understand it. They have assumed
that the misfortunes of the hero and heroine were mainly due to their
own rashness or imprudence in yielding to the impulses of passion
instead of obeying the dictates of reason. They think that the dramatist
speaks through Friar Laurence when he warns them against haste in the
marriage (ii. 6. 9 fol.):--

"These violent delights have violent ends,
And in their triumph die, like fire and powder,
Which as they kiss consume; the sweetest honey
Is loathsome in his own deliciousness,
And in the taste confounds the appetite.
Therefore love moderately, long love doth so;
Too swift arrives as tardy as too slow."

But the venerable celibate speaks for himself and in keeping with the
character, not for Shakespeare.

Neither does the poet, as some believe, intend to read a lesson against
clandestine marriage and disregard for the authority or approval of
parents in the match. The Friar, even at the first suggestion of the
hurried and secret marriage, does not oppose or discourage it on any
such grounds; nor, in the closing scene, does he blame either the lovers
or himself on that account. Nowhere in the play is there the slightest
suggestion of so-called "poetic justice" or retribution in the fate that
overtakes the unhappy pair.

It is the parents, not the children, that have sinned, and the sin of
the parents is visited upon their innocent offspring. This is the burden
of the prologue; and it is most emphatically repeated at the close of
the play.

The feud of the two households and the civil strife that it has caused
are the first things to which the attention of those who are to witness
the play is called. Next they are told that the children of these two
foes become lovers--not foolish, rash, imprudent lovers, not victims of
disobedience to their parents, not in any way responsible for what they
afterwards suffer--but "star-cross'd lovers." The fault is not in
themselves, but in their stars--in their _fate_ as the offspring of
these hostile parents. But their unfortunate and piteous overthrow is
the means by which the fatal feud of the two families is brought to an
end. The "death-mark'd love" of the children--love as pure as it was
passionate, love true from first to last to the divine law of
love--while by an evil destiny it brings death to themselves, involves
also the death of the _hate_ which was the primal cause of all the
tragic consequences.

This is no less distinctly expressed in the last speeches of the play.
After hearing the Friar's story, the Prince says:--

"Where be these enemies?--Capulet!--Montague!
See what a scourge is laid upon your hate,
That heaven finds means to kill your joys with love!
And I, for winking at your discords too,
Have lost a brace of kinsmen; all are punish'd.

_Capulet._ O brother Montague, give me thy hand;
This is my daughter's jointure, for no more
Can I demand.

_Montague._ But I can give thee more;
For I will raise her statue in pure gold,
That while Verona by that name is known
There shall no figure at such rate be set
As that of true and faithful Juliet.

_Capulet._ As rich shall Romeo by his lady lie;
Poor sacrifices of our enmity!"

It is the parents who are punished. The scourge is laid upon their
_hate_, and it was the _love_ of their children by which Heaven found
the means to wield that scourge. The Prince himself has a share in the
penalty for tolerating the discords of the families. "We all," he says,
"_all_ are punished." But the good Friar's hope, expressed when he
consented to perform the marriage,--

"For this alliance may so happy prove
To turn your households' rancour to pure love,"--

is now fulfilled. Both Capulet and Montague, as they join hands in amity
over the dead bodies of their children, acknowledge the debt they owe to
the "star-cross'd" love of those "poor sacrifices of their enmity." They
vie with each other in doing honour to the guiltless victims of their
"pernicious rage." Montague will raise the golden statue to Juliet, and
Capulet promises as rich a monument to Romeo.

Da Porto and Paynter and Brooke, in like manner, refer to the
reconciliation of the rival families as the fortunate result of the
tragic history. Da Porto says: "Their fathers, weeping over the bodies
of their children and overcome by mutual pity, embraced each other; so
that the long enmity between them and their houses, which neither the
prayers of their friends, nor the menaces of the Prince, nor even time
itself had been able to extinguish, was ended by the piteous death of
the two lovers." As Paynter puts it, "The Montesches and Capellets
poured forth such abundance of tears, as with the same they did evacuate
their ancient grudge and choler, whereby they were then reconciled: and
they which could not be brought to atonement[3] by any wisdom or human
counsel were in the end vanquished and made friends by pity." So
Brooke, in his lumbering verse:--

"The straungenes of the chaunce, when tryed was the truth,
The Montagewes and Capelets hath moved so to ruth,
That with their emptyed teares, theyr choler and theyr rage
Was emptied quite; and they whose wrath no wisdom could asswage,
Nor threatning of the prince, ne mynd of murthers donne
At length (so mighty Jove it would) by pitye they are wonne."

And then the poem, like the play, ends with a reference to the
monumental honour done to the lovers:

"And lest that length of time might from our myndes remove
The memory of so perfect, sound, and so approved love,
The bodies dead, removed from vaulte where they did dye,
In stately tombe, on pillers great of marble, rayse they hye.
On every syde above were set, and eke beneath,
Great store of cunning Epitaphes, in honor of theyr death.
And even at this day the tombe is to be seene;
So that among the monumentes that in Verona been,
There is no monument more worthy of the sight,
Then is the tombe of Juliet and Romeus her knight."

[Footnote 2:

"Come see the Capulets and Montagues,--
Monaldi,--Filippeschi, reckless one!
These now in fear, already wretched those."

(Wright's translation.)
]

[Footnote 3: In the original sense of reconciliation; as in _Rich. III_.
i. 3. 36:

"he desires to make atonement
Betwixt the Duke of Gloster and your brothers," etc.
]



ROMEO AND JULIET _DRAMATIS PERSON�_

  ESCALUS, prince of Verona.
  PARIS, a young nobleman, kinsman to the prince.
  MONTAGUE, }
  CAPULET,  } heads of two houses at variance with each other.
  An old man of the Capulet family.
  ROMEO, son to Montague.
  MERCUTIO, kinsman to the prince, and friend to Romeo.
  BENVOLIO, nephew to Montague, and friend to Romeo.
  TYBALT, nephew to Lady Capulet.
  FRIAR LAURENCE, }
  FRIAR JOHN,     } Franciscans.
  BALTHASAR, servant to Romeo.
  SAMPSON, }
  GREGORY, } servants to Capulet.
  PETER, servant to Juliet's nurse.
  ABRAM, servant to Montague.
  An Apothecary.
  Three Musicians.
  Page to Paris; another Page; an Officer.

  LADY MONTAGUE, wife to Montague.
  LADY CAPULET, wife to Capulet.
  JULIET, daughter to Capulet.
  Nurse to Juliet.

Citizens of Verona; Kinsfolk of both houses; Maskers, Guards, Watchmen,
and Attendants.

Chorus.

SCENE: _Verona_; _Mantua_.

[Illustration: THE "MEASURE"]



<prologue>
  <para value="1">
  Two households, both alike in dignity,
    In fair Verona, where we lay our scene,
  From ancient grudge break to new mutiny,
    Where civil blood makes civil hands unclean.
  From forth the fatal loins of these two foes
    A pair of star-cross'd lovers take their life,
  Whose misadventur'd piteous overthrows
    Doth with their death bury their parents' strife.
  </para>
  <para value="2">
  The fearful passage of their death-mark'd love,
   And the continuance of their parents' rage,
  Which, but their children's end, nought could remove,
   Is now the two hours' traffic of our stage,
  The which if you with patient ears attend,
  What here shall miss, our toil shall strive to mend.
  </para>
</prologue>

  
</introduction>